Guide to the Townsend Family Papers, 1829-1972 RL.10990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Townsend Family papers
1829-1972
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Townsend family
RL.10990
2.4 Linear Feet
Consists of genealogical information, correspondence, photographs, diaries, notebooks, and a manuscript autobiography relating to the large Townsend family of Felchville, Vermont.
1699 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Historical note
Residents of Felchville, Windsor County, Vt.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of genealogical information, correspondence, photographs, diaries, notebooks, and a manuscript autobiography relating to the Townsend family of Felchville, Vermont. The bulk of the correspondence between a large group of family members falls between 1830 and 1939; topics include family matters and spiritualism. One group of letters and a diary were written by a Union soldier, Francis Torrey Townsend, and relate to his experiences in Mississippi and Tennessee as a soldier with Company K, 13th Iowa Infantry. Other materials concern Bessie Meachum's teaching experiences with African-American children at the Beach Institute, Savannah, Ga., at the Lincoln Normal School, Marion, Ala., and at the Rio Grande Industrial School in Albuquerque, N.M.; some of this work was done through the American Missionary Association of the Congregational Church. Some photographs also depict Tougaloo College in Miss., and Le Moyne College in Tenn. Other volumes include the early 20th century diaries of Torrey Townsend and his autobiography; an 1870 diary of Elisa Townsend; a 1892 diary of Mary Meachum; and several diaries and notebooks of Bessie Meachum.
Provenance
The Townsend Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1984.
American Missionary Association; African Americans -- Education -- Southern States; Tougaloo College; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Le Moyne College (Memphis, TN); Felchville, VT -- History; Education -- Southern States; Diaries; Soldiers -- Correspondence; Rio Grande Industrial School (Albuquerque,NM); Mississippi -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Lincoln Normal School (Marion, AL); Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Spiritualism; Soldiers -- Diaries; Vermont -- Social life and customs; United States Army -- Iowa Infantry Regiment 13th -- Company K; Women -- Vermont -- Correspondence; Susan T. Fay; Annie A. Townsend; Aurelia T. Herrick; Mary Meachum; Elisa Townsend; Francis Torrey Townsend; Bessie Meachum; Townsend family; Dennis Townsend
- Townsend Family papers, 1829-1972
  - Genealogical information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1829-1862 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1863-1904 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1905-1940 (Box 3)
  - Diaries and journals, 1865-1947 (Box 4)
  - Diaries and journals, 1948-1972 (Box 5)
  - Financial papers (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1880-1920 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1910-1940 (Box 6)